{
  "title": "Algorithms - Sorting — Slot 2 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Sorting — Slot 2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following sorting algorithms.<br>I.\nQuicksort<br>II.  Heapsort<br>III&gt; Mergesort<br>Which of them perform in least time in the worst case? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I, II and III</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/55014/isro2014-62\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>You have an array of n elements. Suppose you implement quick sort by always choosing the central element of the array as the pivot. Then the tightest upper bound for the worst case performance is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{3})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{2})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2048/gate2014-3-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let P be a quick sort program to sort numbers in ascending order using the first element as\nthe pivot. Let t1 and t2 be the number of comparisons made by P for the inputs [1 2 3 4\n5] and [4 1 5 3 2] respectively. Which one of the following holds? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(t_{1}=5\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\lt t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\gt t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(t_{1}=t_{2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\gt t_{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1780/gate2014-1-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following sorting algorithms has the minimum running time complexity in the best and average case? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion sort, Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Quick sort, Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Quick sort, Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Insertion sort, Insertion sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion sort, Quick sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43802/isro-2013-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The number of elements that can be sorted in \\(\\Theta (log n)\\) time using heap sort is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (1)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\sqrt{logn})\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\frac{log n}{log log n})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (log n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\frac{log n}{log log n})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1541/gate2013-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is the tightest upper bound that represents the number of swaps\nrequired to sort n numbers using selection sort? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O(log n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O(n log n)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{2})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1415/gate2013-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A list of n strings, each of length n, is sorted into lexicographic order using the merge-sort\nalgorithm. The worst case running time of this computation is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O (n log n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O (\\(n^{2} log n\\))</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O (\\(n^{2}+ log n\\))</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>O (\\(n^{2}\\))</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>O (\\(n^{2} log n\\))</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1762/gate2012-39#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following algorithm design technique is used in merge sort? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Dynamic programming</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Divide and Conquer</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Divide and Conquer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52859/isro2011-66\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following in place sorting algorithms needs the minimum number of swaps? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Heap sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Selection sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/975/gate2006-14-isro2011-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>In quick sort, for sorting n elements, the (n/4)th smallest element is selected as\npivot using an O(n) time algorithm. What is the worst case time complexity of the quick sort? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2} logn)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1325/gate2009-39#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>What is the number of swaps required to sort n elements using selection sort, in the worst case? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2} logn)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1303/gate2009-11#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>How many comparisons are needed to sort an array of length 5 if a straight selection sort is used  and array is already in the opposite order? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>15</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>20</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>10</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/17268/isro2008-77\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>If we use Radix Sort to sort n integers in the range \\(\\left (n^{k/2}, n^k \\right )\\), for some k&gt;0 which is independent of n, the time taken would be? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(kn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n^2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta(n \\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3353/gate2008-it-43\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the Quicksort algorithm. Suppose there is a procedure for finding a pivot element which splits the list into two sub-lists each of which contains at least one-fifth of the elements. Let T(n) be the number of comparisons required to sort n elements. Then <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq 2T (n/5)+n\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq T (n/5)+T(4n/5)+n\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq 2T (4n/5)+n\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq 2T (n/2)+n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)\\leq T (n/5)+T(4n/5)+n\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/455/gate2008-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>The average case and worst case complexities for Merge sort algorithm are <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O (n^2), O  (n^2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O  (n^2), O (n \\log_2 n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O (n \\log_2 n), O  (n^2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n \\log_2 n), O (n \\log_2 n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n \\log_2 n), O (n \\log_2 n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49624/isro2007-58\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}